Okay, welcome back.
Um
we're going to move away from
pre-training now, and I think we'll get
into
uh in my opinion, some of the messier
parts
um of language modeling. I mean, data is
always pretty messy, but I think
post-training and everything that goes
along with it is really, you know, kind
of artisanal in many ways.
Um so, to set the stage, thus far, I
think you can kind of get to a souped-up
version of GPT-3. Uh I'm sure you can
use more flops, you can get more data.
So, you can make something a little bit
better than GPT-3, but ultimately,
um the amount of utility you can get
from something like GPT-3, which is a
very big, strong base model, is
ultimately a little bit limited, right?
Um when we went from GPT-3 to something
like ChatGPT, um
I'm sure if your first exposure to to
these systems with ChatGPT, it was like
kind of amazing. If you go back and
interact with GPT-3, you'll be like,
"What is What is this thing? What is the
point of this thing?" right? And the
only thing you could really do with it
was things like copywriting or these
like sort of fun little tasks where you
didn't really need reliability or
instruction following.
So, today, we are going to get from
GPT-3 to something that is getting
basically close to ChatGPT, right? So,
this is the very first part that we
need. Um and then the next lecture, we
will go from ChatGPT to
um GPT-01 or, you know, any of the
thinking models that we have today,
right? So, those are going to be the two
parts. And the process that will take us
from the left to the right will be a
process that, you know, usually people
call post-training.
Um and I want to sort of emphasize just
kind of how remarkable it is that we can
do instruction following. Um instruction
following is
um this process of being able to put in
a pretty long, complicated prompt and
get back, you know, very reasonable
answers. Um at the GPT GPT-3 level,
fine-grained control of these systems
was basically impossible. Like you would
put in a bunch of few-shot prompts and
you'd say, "Well, if my examples were
good enough, I'd get something
reasonable." Um, in practice, your
ability to steer these models are
limited. Um, but once GPT-3.5 and GPT-4
comes around, you start getting these
examples of very long sort of
programmatic prompts and then the model
really one-shotting um the whole prompt.
And so, what does it What do you really
need in order to get this kind of
instruction following
um to work?
And so, pre-training is always
important. It's kind of the basis on
which we build all of this, right? So,
if we ignore pre-training and we just
try to post-train our way to victory, we
will get none of the things that we
want. Absolutely none of it. So,
pre-training is critical because it
scales in this very diverse broad way.
Um, but once we have pre-training, we
have to then extract the kinds of
behaviors that we want out of this kind
of primordial soup that is pre-training,
right? Um, and to do that, we are going
to have to do much more explicit data
collection, much more explicit steering,
and a lot of messy engineering that in
some ways we didn't have to do so far. I
mean, the architecture stuff you might
think is messy, I think it really
doesn't compare to the messiness of
real-world post-training.
Um, and so, you know, we're going to go
and collect some data or, you know, we
will talk as if we are going to go and
collect some data. Um, we're going to
talk about what that data looks like,
um, how to train with it, um, and what
the scale of that looks like.
Um, and I will preface the rest of this
lecture and say, you know, information
about frontier post-training is honestly
pretty sparse in many, many ways. If you
look at the the uh materials that I'm
going to reference today, um, a lot of
it's going to be actually pretty old.
It's going to be before the competition
from ChatGPT started to heat up. Um, so,
for example, the RLHF paper, um,
learning to summarize from human
feedback, you know, that that's actually
incredibly detailed. I'll point to that
today in lecture. You know, if you're
interested, I suggest you go read some
of the appendices. You know, it contains
things like detailed annotation
guidelines, how they were instructing
people to to, you know, give feedback to
the models. Similarly with Anthropic's
HH paper back in 2022.
And then, you know, now that competition
has heated up, basically none of the
vendors want to release any information
about their post-training processes,
right? The data is very much a trade
secret.
And so, we are not going to be able to
talk about annotation guidelines and
things like that for anything that
resembles a modern language model.
Um, and you know, we do have
closed-source open-source models,
but on the other hand, a lot of the
open-source recipes rely on
distillation. I think its nature is very
different from what the frontier labs
are doing in terms of like human data
collection, which is really a very
tricky and messy thing. And and I'll try
to point out some of that, but be
difficult to talk about some of that
very comprehensively.
Um, okay. And then, you know, just as an
example of this, you know, I was doing
some pre-research for this lecture
earlier, and I found this very fun
example back in 2023 about, you know,
the trade secretness of post-training
data.
Where I guess, you know, Scale AI's
internal documents got leaked at some
point, and they had a whole bunch of
very frank conversations about what was
happening in post-training data land.
And one of them was like, well, they
were trying to make Google Bard better,
but they couldn't figure out why, you
know, GPT-4 was so much better. And so,
they said, well, let's like we need to
like reverse engineer what's happening,
and we need to get our
annotators to produce responses that are
more detailed or and better than GPT-4,
right? So, these kinds of like
competitive dynamics are happening all
the time, and that's also why some of
this detail is going to be missing from
today's lecture.
Um, that said, algorithm-wise, we do
have a pretty good handle on what is
happening, right? But algorithms are not
really the the secret sauce. It's not
where a lot of the leverage is. It's
going to be the data. Um so, if we look
at um the sort of RLHF papers, we see a
very straightforward recipe, right?
Two-part recipe. The first part is you
go and collect some demonstration data,
right? So, for every sort of prompt, you
want some annotator to provide
supervised fine-tuning data. So, you
know, reference responses for that
prompt, right? And you're going to do
some fine-tuning.
Then after you have that, you're going
to do some reinforcement learning of
some kind to try to shape the behavior
of the model to be sort of more aligned
or more in line with what sort of humans
think are good responses, right? So, I'm
going to start by talking about this
very first phase, which is the SFT part
of um post-training. Um and this is the
part that's really basically all about
data, right? We all know how to SFT a
model. That's basically exactly the same
as pre-training. So, the only real
difference with some minor variation is
going to be the training data. So, I
will focus on the training data almost
entirely for this part um of the
lecture.
Okay.
Um with a little bit of discussion about
the method right after.
Okay.
So, we will go through the data. We're
going to, you know, look at some
examples. I'll talk about some
historical developments and what kind of
the trends are at least in open-source
post-training data land.
Um and then I will talk about some
pitfalls, some ways in which collecting
this kind of data is much harder uh than
you think. And, you know, if you've
taken classes like 224N, um you're going
to sort of find some things that are
very reminiscent of uh issues that you
see when you start building, you know,
classic supervised deep learning models
from scratch.
Um
So, let me take a moment to pause um and
then just talk about the progression of
SFT data over the years. Um
I think I'm going to go, you know, top
left to bottom right. That's roughly my
chronological ordering and there's been
a lot of different tricks and a lot of
things that people have done in the open
source language modeling land to try to,
you know, both improve system
performance and to to try to understand
what factors
of this kind of data are useful to train
models. I think really the oldest and
you know, in some ways the most
visionary of this is things like Flon.
This was used to train the T5 model by
Google. Um, their rough idea for this
was to say, well, NLP people have
already collected a bunch of supervised
data sets of like inputs and outputs. We
should just train the model on all of
these, right? Reasonable thing to try.
Turned out for various reasons this was
not the right thing to do. I'll talk
about that later.
Um, Self-Instruct and other sort of
follow-ups to that. This was also sort
of very forward-looking in terms of its
thinking was saying, well, why can't we
use the model itself to generate data?
Well, models are getting better all the
time. Um, and in fact they might even be
better than some of our annotators. Why
don't we get models to, you know, write
very
very good high-quality responses to our
inputs. And that's sort of the
Self-Instruct idea. And then there came
a bunch of sort of distillation style
approaches. Alpaca is one of them. The
Berkeley folks had one called Vicuna in
which they were using
sort of online user shared prompts as
sort of the way to
as the inputs to distill on.
And then there were sort of other
efforts that were more entirely human
driven like Open Assistant. You can
think of this like kind of like
Wikipedia. It was a bunch of people
getting together to write prompts and
responses.
And then you have sort of a new
generation Wizard LM and Tulu 3 and
others of saying, well, we know that
language models are very good synthetic
data generators. Why don't we come up
with increasingly complicated ways of
generating instruction following data
using language models. And then finally
I'll touch briefly on this, um SFT and
sort of post-training has changed yet
again in recent years because I think
the focus is less on chat and much more
on agents and tool use. And so there is
a now a new generation of sort of SFT
pipelines that are designed to generate
sort of tool use and agentic data,
right? So this is roughly, you know, a
bunch of different developments in uh
post-training data land, at least in the
open-source world.
So in the closed-source world where, you
know, well, some of the companies may be
distilling each other, but where you're
also collecting human data, you know,
how you're collecting the human data is
a big important ingredient that's not
reflected in any of this discussion.
Okay, I can pause here in case anyone
has
uh questions um before I move on to
Well, what we're going to do next is
look at some of the details of these
data sets.
Good. Oh, yeah.
>> So when you do for post-training, we
need the input-output output pairs,
right?
>> That's right. You need input-output
pairs.
>> Like does the correctness of those
input-output matters like how far
>> Yes, so the question was how much does
the correctness of the input-output
pairs matter?
Um that's a nuanced question. I mean, I
think the the top-level answer is you
should go collect the highest quality
responses you can because the bad stuff
will teach the model to do bad stuff. On
the other hand, it turns out that you
can SFT models on all sorts of strange
things and they will learn to follow
instructions. Um
I think
Percy's former student had a paper in
which you're like training uh models
without even the the responses or
something and you can train models to
like, you know, be instruction
following. And so there's a lot of like
pre-training generalization behaviors
that let you get away with worse quality
data. So it's like it's actually a
pretty nuanced question um what you need
in uh instruction following data.
Okay, good.
So um
I want to maybe start with FLAN. Um
you know, I think FLAN is very much like
a forward-looking
uh data set for its time, right? Like it
sort of established this idea of doing
this like multitask post training. Just
if you're going to do downstream tasks,
go collect all the downstream tasks and
train on it. Very reasonable but smart
idea at the time. Um but if we look at
what's in FLAN, we actually find that,
you know, it's a little bit of a strange
data set.
Um you know, you have this thing that's
like, "Well, here's an email." And then
there's this like thing that gets
appended, which is like write a subject
line for this email, and then the
subject line goes on the right. Um this
is a very strange thing. Like I don't
think you've ever probably prompted, you
know, uh model to do a task like this,
let alone the instructions at the very
end, right? And the reason why you get
something like this is because FLAN is
generated from existing data sets,
right? So there's a data set called
Enron emails. This is basically a way to
turn Enron emails into a supervised
task, right? Because it has a body and a
subject, you can make this subject
prediction task. Um you know, similarly,
you know, you have uh summarization
task. This is I don't know if this was
taken from CNN Daily Mail or Exxon, but
it was taken from one of the big major
summarization data sets, right? Write
highlights for this article, take the
article part of a summarization data
set, put the summary summary on the
right. But you immediately notice, you
know, compared to something like
ChatGPT, the summaries are very short.
Um in fact, if you look really closely,
the summaries are often hallucinated.
Like there's a bunch of details that are
not in the inputs.
Um and in some ways, you know, related
to this question, right? The original
NLP data sets from which FLAN was built
was not the highest of quality, right?
And so when you train on this thing, you
also inherit a whole bunch of sort of
deficiencies from those data sets. And
the unnaturalness of the structure of
these data sets also sort of carry down
all the way. Um
and so this is a very smart idea. FLAN
is a very smart idea to create this big
data set out of
um
of these uh
data set existing benchmarks, but really
the unnaturalness really gets you.
Oh, and I'll I'll mention one more thing
going back one slide. I think when FLAN
was originally constructed, sort of part
of the theory of how post-training
should work was that you needed scale,
right? Like in pre-training we know we
need a lot of scale, so you might also
think that in post-training we need a
ton of scale to unlock capabilities. Um
and so because of that they took tons of
data sets and lots of data and had this
gigantic data set. We'll see kind of
later on that a lot of these data sets
just get really much smaller and it
still works. And so really part of the
change from FLAN to later data sets is
this observation that if you have a
sufficiently strong big pre-trained
model, you can actually get away with
very few high-quality examples because
the pre-training generalization is going
to get you quite a bit of the way. And
so it's kind of the wrong point in some
ways on the quality
quantity trade-off, although you know,
there was no way to know until we sort
of explored the full space of these data
sets. Um
and then I think, you know, after that
the the maybe next point in how sort of
instruction tuning data sets our
understanding of it changed
was after ChatGPT came out,
some of my students
you know, did this thing called Alpaca
where they distilled ChatGPT traces to
get input-output pairs, right? Um so
this is an example from that data set.
You get, you know, more natural-looking
inputs,
longer sort of chatty outputs because of
course it's it's taken from ChatGPT.
Um and what we found was that these
kinds of examples now reliably induced
kind of ChatGPT-like behavior on models.
Importantly, you know, only when we did
it to the original Llama models.
So pre-training, post-training, you
know, both of them need to work out
right, but we did find you know, that
this was was kind of the point at which
these things started to work. And so I
think people realized at this point that
if you got this kind of sort of chat
style data, it was actually not that
hard to build chat GPT style systems.
You know, getting the details right is
still hard, but you know, to get most of
the way.
So then I think there was this big push
to create essentially the highest
quality human driven version of this
these kinds of data sets.
Um, to give you a little bit more
context that at the time, I think after
chat GPT came out and Alpaca came out, I
think there was this enormous optimism
that if only we could
collect a sufficiently high quality and
large, you know, instruction tuning data
set, we could then sort of catch up and
match a lot of the performance of these
big closed source labs. So there's a lot
of sort of energy and excitement uh to
building these data sets. And so in that
context, Open Assistant is this big
crowd sourced effort to build such a
data set, right? So a lot of volunteers
got together and they said, well, we're
going to, you know, come up with really
hard and interesting prompts. We're
going to come up with good high quality
responses and we're going to do it at
scale in the same way that Wikipedia,
you know, managed to produce something
very high quality at scale. Um, a very
admirable, very impressive effort um
that generated actually a decent amount
of data. I forget if it's like 10,000 or
more examples um
before sort of stalling out as as a as a
as a project. I can I can maybe, you
know, talk about that if someone's
interested. Um, but if you look now, we
have, you know, chat style inputs, very
long detailed sort of high quality
expert responses on the right. Good
stuff. Um, I'll talk about some of the
pitfalls later as well.
Okay. Finally, I've taken this from some
of the newest of the instruction tuning
data sets. We've really started to move
as a field or, you know, in terms of the
products that people want from just a
chat interface to something that's like
a full agent system, right? So we don't
want just textual responses, we want
tool calls, we want, you know, uh to-do
lists. If you've ever used Claude code
or Codex, you know that like it produces
a to-do list to like check off as it
goes. Um, we want all of those things,
right? And so, SFT data now, if you look
at, for example, Nemotron, so that's
Nvidia's open source efforts, their SFT
data, uh, a big chunk of it is these
kinds of agentic SFT, uh, examples,
where not only do you have the
responses, which are provided in the
sort of, uh, assistant field here, um,
but also tool calls that can happen in
parallel alongside the text, right? And
this is SFT data, so this is, you know,
explicitly sort of supervised into the
model.
Um,
and so, now we're sort of moving much
more towards these like structured, uh,
formats.
Okay. And I've been talking about this
as I've gone through, but we've seen
sort of big, sort of higher-level
transitions in how we think about and
build these kinds of data sets. It's
useful to roughly internalize these sort
of like perspectives. Um, one of them is
kind of this chattiness thing. Um, it's
hard for me to like fully articulate
what this is, but there is a sense in
which the classic NLP data sets, even
the high-quality ones, were very like
input to like programmatic output
almost, right? Um, but people don't
really want to talk to an NLP benchmark.
They want to talk to people. And so,
there was this big shift that has
happened towards more detailed
human-like responses.
Um, there's a big shift towards
higher-quality annotators and much more
detail. Open Assistant is a good example
of this, of having experts write your
responses. And then finally, you know,
tool use and figuring out the right sort
of, you know, interface and API for all
of this has been a big, sort of final
shift that's been happening. I'm sure
things will keep changing, but these are
kind of some high-level, you know,
factors, uh, to think about, uh, in
terms of how SFT data has changed over
the last few years.
Okay.
Um, I'll talk about, sort of, all sorts
of,
you know, pitfalls or challenges in a
moment. Um,
any questions on on the specifics of
data sets and things like this?
Good. Okay.
Um, so now, I think, let's say you are
put in charge of collecting human
annotation data for SFT.
Um, what kinds of sort of things should
you be mindful of, right? Um, there's
lots of formatting things, right, that
you might want to think about. There's
also things like knowledge. How much
knowledge should be put into the
responses? How many how much data points
do you want? And like how do you deal
with kind of
uh safety of your model? Like what kinds
of safety data should you be collecting?
Um
And I think one thing I want to
highlight is
length is and style variation in general
is a very, very big part of this like
post-training process. People say, you
know, Claude has a different tone than
ChatGPT, you know, ChatGPT is too
chatty, so on and so forth. All of these
are, you know, conscious decisions that
are made by the data collection folks.
Um, and also we see like very wide
variation if you look at the data sets
in terms of the length of the responses.
Um, and one thing I do want to kind of
highlight is when you go and evaluate
preferences,
um, these stylistic factors matter a
ton, right? So, people will get very
easily tricked not I don't know if
tricked is the right word. You know,
they will very often select responses
that have bullet-pointed lists in their
outputs. Uh, or they will select
responses that have, you know, more and
longer detail. I think part of this is
very natural, especially if you're in a
evaluation setting where you put in
front of two examples and someone asks
you which one's better. I think, you
know, more detailed and list-like
responses are generally good, um, but
this does induce very explicit
distortions in the kinds of, you know,
uh tone that a chatbot has, uh relative
to people.
Um
These factors Oh, yeah.
>> So, how do complex models differ in the
data sets?
>> I'll talk about that later.
Um, and you can ask me questions if I
don't fully answer your question there.
Um,
so
Uh,
right. But, I think the thing about
style, right? And the thing to be
careful about is if you're looking at
engagement signals, as most of these
companies are, um, it's very, very easy
to fool yourself into thinking you're
getting better data, when in reality,
um, your model's capabilities are not
changing. So, if you look at sort of all
of these different kinds of like, you
know, uh, post-training data sets that
you can train on, um, you'll see big
variations in preferences when you train
on some of these things. kind of the
right column over there, Alpaca Eval,
for example. But, really it doesn't
necessarily change, you know, standard
benchmarking evaluations. So, your
models aren't necessarily smarter
because you've trained on certain kinds
of post-training data, at least in these
ones. Um, but you can very much shift
sort of the engagement signals. And so,
this is kind of telling you, you know,
you want to think about style control
separately from capabilities control.
Okay. The other thing, and this I think
is a is a quite, in many ways, important
sort of thing to think about in terms of
how we collect and think about
post-training data.
Um, I think OpenAssistant is very
instructive because it was an effort
that was, you know, intended to be the
highest-quality, in some ways, uh,
post-training data. Um, and so, you
often see things like this. Like, for
example, this res- uh, reference, I
should say, this response contains a
reference to an article, this J.
Michelle L., The Pay of Corporate
Executives and blah, blah, blah, right?
Um, and so, this is actually teaching
the model kind of two different things
at once. Let's say you you're uh,
SFT'ing on this data. So, first of all,
you know, you're doing next token
prediction, so it's teaching the model
about, you know, this Bivens, J. and
Michelle, L. citation. Um, it's also
telling the model another thing, which
is when you're giving a response, a good
thing to do is to give a reference,
right?
So, these are two different mechanisms
that are sort of going on at once.
You're teaching the model about
different pieces of knowledge, which is
good because you want the model model to
be knowledgeable, but you're also
teaching the model to emit detailed
knowledge. Um and this is sometimes
problematic, because what this is going
to force the model to do is sometimes it
will misgeneralize and it will sort of
hallucinate out a reference instead of
actually giving a proper reference,
right? Models don't really know
necessarily whether a reference is uh
true or false. Um and there's been sort
of a lot of interesting arguments that
people have made around this. Um
And I think the folklore, which I think
is not wrong, there's some, you know,
good empirical evidence to support this
folklore, is that if you train a model,
especially at the SFT phase, to uh emit
facts that it does not know, um this
will make it hallucinate.
Right? Because the model, as I said, is
trying to generalize two behaviors at
once. It's trying to generalize the
knowledge, but also the format. And so
teaching it something where you have the
format and a sort of piece of unknown
knowledge is kind of teaching the model
to forcibly emit unknown knowledge. Um
and people have shown that if you train
on, for example, um
information that that you don't really
know, then this leads to sort of
hallucination and sort of overfitting uh
to pieces of knowledge, whereas if
you're training on only known facts, you
don't necessarily see this. Um John
Schulman makes a a sort of separate
argument, which is that this is the
reason why you need reinforcement
learning in training. I mean, this is
not surprising, because if you know John
Schulman, he's like a reinforcement
learning guy, right? Like he made PPO.
You know, of course, he is very pro
reinforcement learning, but the argument
is sound, right? That in some ways, in
order to teach the model what it knows
and doesn't know, you do have to be
policy dependent, right? You can't have
an external person telling like sort of
shoving knowledge down your throat if
you want the model to be sort of
calibrated about what it knows and
doesn't know.
Okay.
Um and so to put that piece together,
right? Um you might not want to train on
the highest-quality data if the model
doesn't already know that data, right?
Tail knowledge can actually sometimes be
actively harmful in that it might induce
hallucinations, especially if it's
associated with markers like reference
colon, right? That that'll force the
model to emit a reference afterwards.
Um I'll talk about RLHF later, but you
know, this is one of the reasons why
reinforcement learning is important and
useful, right? For things that are model
dependent, like knowing what you know,
RL is a very useful way to teach models
to not say things that it does not know.
Um
And so, knowledge storage is actually
very messy and a very nuanced concept.
Um you don't really want to just say,
"Ah, yes, just pack knowledge in there."
You want to be very careful about
exactly what supervision you're throwing
in at the post-training stage. This is
one of the reasons why I think
post-training is quite messy, right? You
have to deal with all these realities of
serving a system eventually to a user.
Yes.
>> What's the definition of tail knowledge?
>> Yeah, I don't think there is like a
formal definition of tail knowledge. For
example, in the past when I've worked on
things like this, um it's been things
like uh the number of times that uh
sorry, the length uh of a Wikipedia
article, for example, might be a proxy
for its, you know, well-knownness. And
then you might say, "Ah, yes, if we
train on stuff that's not well-known, we
do see that the model hallucinates more,
right?" But there's no formal like, "Ah,
yes, this is tail and this is not um
knowledge." Because knowledge itself
can't really be pinned down precisely.
Okay.
Okay, yeah.
>> How does RL get connected to
models hallucinating?
>> Like what what is it?
I'm being too cheeky.
>> The question was what Why would RL help
for hallucinations? Um and the reason
why RL might help, um let me give kind
of like a folk story for why this might
help. Imagine um the model has internal
to it like a I know something direction
inside its activations, right? Yeah, SFT
time, maybe what's happening is you
forced it to, you know, generate
references from your SFT data. And so,
you know, it's just going to generate
references no matter what. But when you
are out, you might notice that you get
good rewards when you generate
references in the I know stuff
direction, and you get bad, you know,
rewards when you generate references in
the I don't know direction. And so, then
you might then learn to generalize that
like I know things or don't know things
activations into whether you emit a
reference. Right? So, it's possible that
if you know what you know somewhere
inside the model, RL can help you
extract that into your output policy. If
you don't know what you know at all,
right, at any level, RL cannot help you
there, right? Like it can't help you
with the problem of like having some
level of calibration.
Yeah.
>> So, just to follow up on that, but if in
the middle of that
reference were to get penalized in the
SFT setting,
>> Um, in in SFT, well, you in some ways
implicitly you're getting penalized for
um
anything that is not a reference. Like
assigning any probability mass to
something that is not this exact
sequence is penalized, right? So, in
some ways SFT isn't doing the wrong
thing. Like this is a correct sequence.
The problem with SFT is the
generalization properties of this. Um,
that, you know, I can't perfectly
generalize off this one example. You
know, there's two things, two sort of
disentangled things that are being
taught here. One is sort of the
reference template, and then the other
thing is
uh the actual content of the knowledge.
Um, and if I misgeneralize based on the
template, I'm in big trouble.
Great great questions. Yeah.
Okay.
Um, the other thing that I want to talk
about is safety, right? Um, and once we
get the post training, we have to really
start engaging with all of the messy
realities of like how are people going
to use this? I think pre-training people
live in this like ivory tower of like
let's just compress the world. But,
post-training people have to say like,
"Oh, yes, but what if, you know, um
people are using our system for uh
political manipulation and
disinformation?" And post-training
people might say, "Oh, yes, we see
individualized spear fishing." You know,
we need to prevent this from happening,
right? Like you you're the last line of
defense in some ways uh between you and
misuse of the system. And so what do you
do? Well, you have to apply safety
controls to the system, right? That will
refuse to respond to sort of malicious
inputs. Like this is kind of the de
facto way by which these companies
enforce the safety controls. And so it
falls upon the post-training team.
Um unfortunately, uh safety SFT
information seems even more sparse than
uh capabilities SFT information in
publicly available documents. Um I you
know, pulled out the Llama 2 description
of how they do safety SFT. If anything,
this is one of the more detailed
descriptions. Um but you'll see that
they don't even talk about how many
examples they used for safety tuning,
which is kind of crazy to me. Um but
regardless, really the the framework by
which all the safety tuning approaches
operate, it's to balance two things. You
want to sort of balance like how often
am I allowing bad queries to get
through, which is I think the violation
rate here. Um and then you also want to
not over refuse because someone might
ask a question like how do I kill a
Python process? And then if your bot's
like, "No, I can't let you kill
anything." That's very frustrating to
the user. And so the false refusal rate
also needs to be low. So you want to
sort of control this and have a good
sort of Pareto trade-off um between the
two.
Um and so what you do is you know, you
basically create various kinds of
tailored data to navigate this
trade-off. Um in terms of the scale of
the amount of data you collect, um you
usually have something like a few
thousand or tens of thousands of
examples. Um for example, in Llama 2, I
think it's about a few thousand examples
that are used for this process.
Um
This state of affairs is a little bit
unsatisfying if I left you with only
that slide. So I will talk a little
about a little bit more detail. Um
I think if you want to look at um how
post-training is done, maybe the only
good reference right now would be Tulu
3. Uh this would be the post training
pipeline for um the Olmo models that
that Allen AI put out. Um and given the
lack of details about post training in
many places, this is one of the few
places where you can see like a, you
know, reasonably performant post
training pipeline in action. Um and they
do have, for example, a safety
component, which consists of something
like, you know, 50-ish thousand examples
uh total. Um and if you look, they all
follow the same fairly simple strategy
for generating SFT data, which is kind
of the following. Um in a previous
project, they they had this thing called
WildChat, where basically they gave free
API or free chat access to a bunch of
people so that they can go out and use
various kinds of chat interactions. Um
and in exchange, they collected, you
know, what they were doing on those
chats. Um and from that, they were able
to basically, you know, filter out a
whole bunch of, you know, sort of unsafe
behaviors that were being attempted to
be done on these chat interfaces, as
well as jailbreaks that people attempted
to do. And so they mined these at scale
and then created essentially the
preferred response, which is to, you
know, resist the jailbreak in one case
and to say no in another case, right?
Fairly very straightforward approach.
And I think from what we see, at least
in the um sort of uh technical reports
and the model cards of the various close
source companies, similar things are
happening in that you look at sort of
the use your usage information, you find
unsafe behaviors, you get your
annotators to uh sort of what play
whack-a-mole um with these bad
behaviors.
Okay. The final thing I'll mention, and
this is related to what I said about,
you know, the number of examples that
you need for SFT. I think one thing, if
you haven't played with SFT before, that
you will be surprised by is if you have
a sufficiently capable model, it does
not take very many examples to steer
these systems. So if you want to do
something like safety tuning, if you
take 500 examples, let's say, you know,
kind of in the vein of, you know, you
find a bunch of unsafe stuff or you
synthesize a bunch of unsafe stuff and
then you write refusals and you put that
into the system, you'll find that even
with as little as 500 examples, um the
rate at which you follow malicious
instructions or other kinds of, you
know, hate speech instructions and so on
drops dramatically, right? And with 500
examples, you're you're really applying
this fairly surgical
not surgical, very small push to the
model, but that results in a fairly nice
across-the-board reduction in these
safety issues um
over here. And so, one way to think
about it is models already have a, you
know, am I going to be a safe safe model
or an unsafe model access inside of it
after pre-training, so it does not take
very many examples to pull this out.
Now, um one thing to to also remember at
the the end of this is just because you
can steer model with very few examples,
that doesn't mean that there's no
benefit to more examples. If you're
OpenAI or Anthropic and you want to
enforce really fine-grained distinctions
about what is safe and not safe, you do
need very large-scale data collection.
This this doesn't really change that
that story.
Okay.
Um so, SFT at its best is kind of this
thing where if you're extracting
pre-training behaviors, like it's
already in there somewhere in
pre-training and all you want to do is
sort of pull out the right modes out of
the model, then instruction fine-tuning
um works very very well. With very
little data, as long as you have the
right high-quality ones, um you can get
the model to do what you want, right? Um
and adding data or factually correct
ones can sometimes hurt you, at least in
terms of hallucination. And then
finally, you know, it doesn't take very
much data and so you can often focus on
quality instead of quantity.
Good. Okay, this is going to be the end
of the data part for SFT, so if anyone
has questions, um ask me before I move
on.
Oh, yes.
>> How do we know what is like already a
behavior
>> Yeah, the the question was like, how do
you know whether something is in
pre-training?
I think this is this is the sloppiness
of what I was saying which is that we
don't really know per se.
We can know what things aren't in
pre-training, right? Like we can look
for the kinds of generalization to like
for example programming languages that
are very rare. That's very hard using
SFT. So we we can show those things. We
can't show necessarily that like for
example safety is something that's in
pre-training per se.
Yes.
>> Can you talk more about this when you
talk about RL but there's a whole
question of like SFT destroying
features where the RL is deleting them.
That's like
Maybe we can talk about that later.
>> I'm not going to talk about that later.
The question was whether SFT is
destroying features and RL is like
pushing up or down.
Um
I think the lines are very blurry
between the two to be honest especially
when we get into something like expert
iteration and all these other things
that look like SFT with extra bells and
whistles. So I don't necessarily think
it's a core distinction between RL and
SFT rather that it's more of a
distinction in the kinds of feedback
that we get, right? SFT is this dense
teacher supervision whereas RL is sort
of the self-taught
policy supervision. And the other thing
about RL is that you know RL is that
you're you're getting your own output
from your own policy. So there's a sense
in which you don't maybe deviate quite
as far in what you're being reinforced
on. So in that's probably an important
part of what's happening. Okay.
So now let's talk about methods. You
know for most of this class we've been
excited to talk about methods. In this
part it is about the most boring thing
because you just do gradient descent. I
just put the picture here as almost a
joke. You know you just take loss dot
backwards and that's basically it. But
there is one nuance I do want to talk
about that is important.
Um which is this increasing trend of
turning instruction tuning into part of
pre-training.
It used to be that when when these
things first appeared that pre-training
and post-training were just these be
ideas
that you would pre-train on web data and
then you would post-train afterwards.
But people realized why separate two
things when you can mix them together.
And so lots of high-quality data and
even instruction tuning data is now
getting mixed in at the tail end of
training when the decay phase usually of
training happens. And this really allows
you to scale up instruction tuning. It
also allows you to essentially emphasize
higher quality data. The impact of this
has been quite dramatic. And so everyone
as far as I know is doing it. You can
see it in most of the
sort of model release reports that
there's a mid-training or like a second
phase pre-training with a different data
mix.
And importantly, one thing that I'll
sort of this is my pet peeve, I'll say
is that now, you know, when someone
tells you something is a base model, you
know, that's kind of a lie because a
base model is usually about like oh yes,
predicting the next word on internet
data or something. Well, really base
models today are pre-trained on like
ultra chat and like who knows what else.
Those are like chat data sets that are
like synthetically designed to make you
good at chat. And so it's very hard to
say that this is like a base model in
the traditional sense of the word. I've
taken this example of a of a two-phase
training. I think this one's from mini
CPM
because I think they show very nicely
sort of the change in the mix. So this
first part is, you know, the very
standard oh whoops, standard
pre-training phase where you got all
sorts of internet data on the left. And
on the right, you're kind of switching
to
this higher quality and also very chatty
data set. You've got like Stack Exchange
QA, you've got ultra chat, you've got
all sorts of other SFT data, and then
you've decreased the fraction of
standard general purpose pre-training
data.
So almost everyone does this today. You
can kind of think of, you know, the
point of this is saying, well, the
boundaries between pre-training and
instruction tuning and also high-quality
data is just being blurred very much. Um
yes.
Are the queries masked in this kind of
data? No, this is pure pre-training. And
so, you know, you're also
predicting the prompt as well.
Um but actually that's not a huge
difference because some SFT recipes do
also predict the prompt.
Yes.
Yeah, okay. So, the question was whether
the data quality is lower in the decay.
Usually the intuition is you want the
reverse. That the decay is the most
important part of your training. It's
the part that's closest to deployment
during pre-training. Also, it's the part
with the lowest learning rate. Um and
so, for both of those reasons, maybe you
want to put the highest-quality stuff
into the decay.
Um
and so, you know, I guess I guess book
Chinese and and all these things are
supposed to be higher quality. Certainly
Wiki and Stack Exchange is usually
considered high quality.
Yes.
>> How is the mixture just I guess for
pre-training you discussed how the
mixture is decided based on the dual
architecture models and everything
used to be announced and decided. But
then I guess for like mid-training and
post-training you have to essentially
run on the larger model or do people
still have like some smaller model that
is a proxy? I assume there's like some
reduction of the amount of information
you can get out of it. I guess you
mentioned like what's the idea about
these data mixtures and where they come
from.
>> Yeah. So, um data mixtures, I mean, both
for pre-training and post-training are
very trial and error, right? Um we do
have algorithms. Like many people have
written papers about things in this
space. Um but I think they're fairly
unreliable. There's a lot of trial and
error and intuition that happens for
this space. Um
but the nice thing about this two-phase
training and this like sort of
mid-training stuff is that mid-training
is much shorter than full pre-training.
So, if you're doing data mix
optimization for mid-training, you can
run like something like 10 of these for
each one of these on the left, right? Um
and so this lets you not quite brute
force the problem, but it does let you
try a lot of ablations.
Um and so actually I think the the usual
way that I've heard a lot of this done
is actually in the decay phase you do a
lot of data ablations, which are cheap
to run and so on. And then you get
estimates of data quality, and then you
reflect that even back to the first
state. Um
into the pre-training stage. Yeah. So to
decide the the pre-training mix, often
you actually run a bunch of ablations on
decay, and then you will figure out what
to put back or to how to set the uh
pre-training mix. The reason why you
don't just make pre-training high
quality is you just don't have enough
tokens, right? You run out of tokens if
you if you try to make Wikipedia your
whole pre-train.
>> Is there any intuition that it's based
on like
from I guess how good the data on which
was which was the primary mixture? Is
there any intuition with how those are
like how they're allocated, I guess?
>> That's very case-by-case of like how you
go from like downstream deltas on
ablations to mixes. There are systematic
ways, like you can fit models and do
these things, but they're often brittle.
Like what I've heard from from people is
that actually it's much more
trial-and-error than you think. Like you
ablate a domain, you make rankings over
which which ablations have the most
impact, um and then you kind of decide
what to put in. Um actually a good
example of this, a fun example of this
that's been leaked is um when uh Meta
got sued for using books. Um in the
court documents, there's actually a
bunch of documents showing, you know,
some researchers doing ablations and
trying to estimate like how useful are
each of these like book subsets. And so
that's exactly the kinds of things that
happen. And then ultimately they'll
decide based on that what the mixes are.
Cool. Okay.
Um so now we're done with SFT. Um
the algorithm part was very short. And
now we get to talk about RLHF. So this
is the second phase. We're done with
sort of doing supervised fine-tuning.
Now we're going to do something very
different from pre-training, where we're
just going to upweight or downweight
different model outputs based on how a
rater, or in in some cases a reward
model, decides how good these responses
are. And before we get into like
algorithms and stuff,
I do want to pause for one moment on
this slide and kind of talk about a
conceptual difference that I think is
actually quite important. Um maybe it's
less important for people that weren't
like originally coming from sort of
stats ML background and so on. But I
think there's actually a very different
sort of way of thinking about SFT or
even pre-training and RLHF. Right? So,
in pre-training, what are we doing?
We're doing generative modeling of some
sequence, right? So, you have a
collection of sequences and you're
trying to predict the next word, right?
SFT is also the same. You've changed the
distribution, but you're predicting the
next word, right? Um so, you can think
about this using your generative
modeling brain, right? This is purely a
generative modeling problem, and then
you're just going to fit some
distribution. Now, once we get to the
second part, the RLHF, we are no longer
playing a fit a distribution game. We
are fitting a maximize a reward game,
right?
Um so, what we want is we want to find
some distribution. We still have a
distribution, right? This is a policy
now, such that this policy is going to
maximize some downstream reward, right?
And maybe that reward is something like,
you know, how long your users are
engaged on your platform, maybe that
reward is like what math problems you
can solve, but there's some sort of
reward. And I don't care if I've
mimicked some distribution, right? And
this is conceptually very different,
because now in the second world, I can
totally collapse out my distribution
onto a single point for every input,
right? So, for every prompt, my model
could have a single answer, right? Not a
distribution. And that would be okay, as
long as it got a good reward, right?
Um so, that's a big important sort of
conceptual distinction to to sort of
keep in your mind, um and I wanted to
highlight it before we get into some of
the later bits.
Okay. So, now, why do we want to sort of
do this thing of doing reinforcement
learning. Um we could just say, "Why
don't you forever go and collect
um you know, SFT data?" Well, I think
one thing that is important for thinking
about RL is when we try to optimize what
humans want, there is sometimes a big
difference in what they say they want
and what they sort of generate.
Um and that's one thing that we found in
the past study. I put this here because
I find this so funny even though it's a
little bit old now. Um we asked a bunch
of freelance writers to uh summarize
news documents.
Um and we found that a few annotators
actually preferred um
which was the predecessor to ChatGPT, uh
over their own writing. Um and that was
very strange and we were like, "Are
these guys actually doing annotations?"
So we interviewed them and we we asked
them like, "You know, why did you like
the AI outputs over your own writing?"
And they they said, "Well, you know, I
looked at it and I thought, actually,
this is pretty good stuff." And so, it
turned out that, you know, they're
they're writers. They're good They're
good at writing. Their summaries are
high quality. Like, we checked it for
quality. But actually, when they looked
at it, they were like, "Huh, I did not
realize that was that's actually a
better way of doing it, right?" So
people aren't really these like optimal
systems. And so, you know, when they
judge things, it's actually different.
And so, because of this gap, sometimes
you might want to to rate outputs rather
than just to generate demonstrations.
Another reason is that um
in some domains, verification is a lot
easier than generation. Uh math, which
I'll talk about a lot uh more uh next
lecture, is a prime example of this,
where you know, verifying a proof is
probably much easier than generating the
proof. And and folks like Deep Seek have
sort of gone down that path for like
self-verification using models. Um
that's another place where this idea of
sort of having reinforcement learning
and judging yourself is a good idea.
So okay. Um I'm not going to cover what
people call RLVR today. That's its own
universe. Um it's going to be an an
lecture next time. I'll talk about the
exciting, you know, promises of
reasoning models.
Um but today I'm going to talk about
RLHF. Um and RLHF will have different
components and I'm going to talk about,
you know, data, like how do we collect
it, um and then I'm going to talk about
algorithms, like how do we actually do
it? And I'll talk about two major
families of algorithms um before sort of
talking about maybe some pitfalls at the
very end. Okay.
Good.
So, in RLHF, right, the high-level way
that we do things is now we have a good
model after SFT that follows some
instructions. We now put prompts into
the model. The model is going to
generate a couple different outputs and
we usually do this by just sampling with
temperature one, right? At the end of
SFT, the model is pretty diverse, so
this is a reasonable thing to do.
A rater comes in and rates all of the
examples um and provides a ranking over
the examples,
um sometimes even a binary ranking, and
then a model is going to be trained on
those rankings, and we're going to use
standard reinforcement learning
techniques to maximize the score that we
get on that reward model.
And, you know, we go through the reward
model because um it might be easier to
train a verifier than to train a model
that does well directly.
Okay, so how do we get data for this
thing?
Um as I said before, the general way in
which we do this is to get pairwise
ratings. And so, you know, you're going
to have an interface like this where,
you know, you have a couple AI responses
and you're going to give a response
saying response one or two is better. Um
this is just a standard annotation
interface that I, you know, uh gone and
found, but
most places have similar things.
We can now look at what, you know, an
actual company would do in order to do
this. It's not that different, although
they have some nuances. Um if you want
to go and like really read up on this, I
would suggest you look at the
InstructGPT appendix. It's kind of the
last point at which we have a glimpse
into
uh data collection, you know, processes
from industry. Um and so, at least in
the InstructGPT case, they say, "Okay,
we want you to rate these outputs for
being helpful, truthful, and harmless."
So, they have to balance three things.
Um helpfulness is like how clear the
writing is or, you know, being sensitive
to internationality or not giving overly
long answers. You want to be truthful,
so don't hallucinate. And then harmless,
you know, if it's unsafe, we want you to
say that, you know, or we want you to,
you know, upweight things that are sort
of refusing to respond to questionable
prompts. So, this sort of makes sense as
a odd omnibus objective for training
chatbots.
Um another very similar example um that
I found is
uh this is I think the only other
example of a of a closed-source lab
annotation uh being out in the public.
Um this one is for Google Bard. That was
a a quite a while ago, but their
annotations got leaked by some
annotators. Um and you can see they have
a very similar structure of saying like
we want helpfulness, we want the
presentation of the response to be good.
And actually, they're rating in a Likert
scale rather than pairwise feedback. Um
but they have a very similar structure.
It's not a very super long set of
instructions, but you get the sense of
like what kinds of things are included
like, you know, don't contain inaccurate
information or be coherent and be sort
of uh
uh easy to consume, so short uh for the
user to read.
Um things have changed quite a bit since
then. Um there are a couple of different
surveys of uh annotators. I think the
high-level thing that I'll say before
going through the next two slides is in
general, I think the worker distribution
for annotation has shifted upwards, more
towards experts, more towards higher
cost. Um and we kind of see that in
compensation and things like this. So,
um if you look at the education level of
data annotators, this is for one of
Scale AI's platform, so it's not, you
know, representative of the full space
of data annotators for language models,
uh but this is probably a reasonable
subset of those. Um the majority or a
large fraction of them uh are bachelor's
degrees or master's holders. So, that's
like 70 some percent of these
annotators.
Um and the age is like something like 35
uh is sort of the modal age. Um and the
task that they're doing are often like,
you know, creative writing and technical
writing and so on, um are often the the
task that these annotators end up
performing.
Um
this is, you know, one step towards
experts, but I think even more, uh
there's been a growth in the last year
or two in kind of bespoke annotators.
And I think this is because a lot of the
labs are now pushing into deploying
these systems in like actual, you know,
white-collar jobs. And so, you want
doctors, you want lawyers, you want
these people to annotate the responses,
you want them to give SFT data.
Um and so, uh there are these projects,
you know, that are internal to these uh
companies like OpenAI, where annotators
are being paid, you know, a pretty
decent wage uh per hour to do these
annotations. And so, um if you look at
sort of the median wages, they're, you
know, above $50 um across a range of
different topics. But, if you look at
the experts, um some of these experts
are being paid, you know, hundreds of or
more than $100
to do annotation work. And so, I think
um
this is to say, if your mental model of
an annotator was like, you know,
low-cost um
uh pairwise feedback from somewhere
overseas, that's not really the full
picture. Um there's a lot of annotation
happening that right now that's like
very bespoke, very expensive, um but
it's kind of also a pyramid. It's not
like that that lower-cost scalable
annotation has gone away.
Okay.
Um and to, you know, uh emphasize this
point to you, getting this kind of data
is actually very challenging. That's why
the pay is high, that's why there's so
many data collection startups. Um
I think that the hard challenges now is
getting sort of verifiable annotators,
especially ones where, you know, you're
sure that they're not using AI. Um if
you all have done like survey research
or crowdsourcing recently, um I'm sure
you found that you know people are using
chat GPT as part of their survey
responses or as part of their annotation
workloads. Basically, preventing people
from doing this is extremely extremely
difficult. Um it's also very difficult
to get truly correct responses when
people are under time pressure.
Um for example, that Google Bard sort of
example, um that was part of I think
some labor dispute where um the
annotators for Google Bard were saying
we have to check the correctness of
these long chat responses in under a
minute, it's impossible for us to do
that. You know, there's no way that we
can actually follow these instructions.
Um
and to add, right, there's a growing
amount of sort of the expert uh data
collection, but there's also a very
large amount still of sort of low-paid
um annotation uh
groups. Um Scale AI, I think they did
quite a bit of this initially. I don't
know if they still do. Um where they
outsourced a lot of this low-cost uh
annotation and got into quite a bit of
trouble. And so, in the same way that I
guess the the modern economy has like
this bifurcation um in terms of like,
you know, high and low wage jobs, we see
the same thing with annotations as well.
The final thing I want to talk about in
terms of um
annotators is demographics. Um one thing
that's quite important is that
annotators have a surprising amount of
influence over what the model does,
right? So, post-training kind of comes
at the end, and it's in some sense the
the final sort of shaping step of the
model before it gets shipped out. So, if
you know, you're not really precise with
how the annotators sort of steer the
model, and your your annotation groups
have biases, you can actually end up
getting some like pretty surprising
behavior. So, one of the studies that we
did um in the early days of instruction
tuning um with one of my postdocs
between Percy and I um
uh was that uh we looked at essentially
which kinds of sort of ideological
opinions language models were more
aligned to. And we did this by like
asking sort of standard opinion poll
questions to language models and seeing
which human demographics they were
closest to. And so what you find or what
we found is that base models of various
kinds were kind of similar to like
Protestants or Roman Catholic opinions
um and kind of far from Buddhist or
Hindu ones. Um and then uh what we found
Oh, sorry. Is that if you post-train
these models, so the the three right
columns, you find that they're, you
know, more different from Protestants
and Roman Catholics um and becomes more
similar to Boo- Buddhists, Hindus, and
atheists in terms of the kinds of
opinions that they give. And we're like,
"Huh, that's really strange. Why these
three groups?" Um it turns out, you
know, if you look at the appendix of the
Instruct GPT paper, um you find the
annotation annotators who were
annotating for these models and they
kind of line up, right? Like a lot of
Southeast Asians um and also people in
the West Coast of America. And that's
roughly the, you know, uh demographic
groups corresponding to these. Um
You also find, I guess, uh another added
note is in the recent years there's been
a lot of findings that, you know, sort
of very subtle biases can transmit
through data. So one example of this is
something called emergent misalignment,
right? If you have a piece of data um
trained from a model or generated from a
model that's been sort of trained to say
like I like owls or something and you
train on that like innocuous-looking
data, the model trained on it will
actually inherit a preference for owls.
And so there's all these like weird
kinds of like subliminal transfer
effects that can happen with data um
that are quite hard to catch. And so
that's one thing to be really, really
quite careful about.
Um and this is true more generally. I
think this whole, you know, study of
like LM political opinions and so on can
be like quite fragile and sketchy at
times. Um but uh the annotator
distribution and who your annotators are
also matters quite a bit for the
different kinds of error uh different
kinds of like more material errors that
your model might make. So this is a
study that's quite nice uh by Hosking et
al. Um where they studied like, if I get
really expert annotators, like people
who like really care about doing the job
right, versus, you know, sort of random
collection of crowdworkers, how do their
annotations differ? Um and they see show
very nice striking results that people
who are just, you know, non-expert
annotators that are just kind of paid on
a platform, really like to emphasize
formatting effects, um which is kind of
this row over here. You see it's red
it's over enriched in sort of these like
non-expert annotators. On the other
hand, things like factuality or
inconsistency are things that are much
more over much more emphasized in the
expert annotators. Of course, it's much,
much harder to test for factuality, and
so it's no surprise that, you know, if
you don't have experts, you don't
actually end up checking for these. This
is another way in which sort of your
your distribution of annotators ends up
mattering. Not demographic, but here, um
how much they care and how what their
expertise is.
Um
it's been shown for a while now that
because of all these like, oh, was there
a question? Yeah.
>> I was I was going to ask how do you
measure quality in
annotators?
What does it mean for one to be higher
quality than
>> Yeah. So, so the question was what does
it mean for one annotator to be higher
quality than another? Um I think there's
no gold standard rule where, you know,
you can kind of mechanically turn the
crank and be like, you are a good
annotator. I think that I'll maybe give
two different kinds of answers. One of
them is, um a sufficiently detailed
annotation guideline should hopefully be
like semi-objective. Like, you know, you
will say like it should be factual, and
then you'll define what factuality is,
and then you might even have objective
criteria. Like, in the first three pages
of the Google search, you don't find
anything that contradicts it, right? And
if you can find something that, you
know, doesn't follow the guideline, you
can be like, ah yes, you're not
following the rule. That's one notion of
a good annotator. The other notion of a
good annotator um is inter-annotator
agreement, right? Um and that's a
statement about a population of
annotators, whether they have high
variance or not. I think the only issue
with that is it doesn't tell you what
the bias is. It tells you the variance,
right? And some tasks inherently have
variance. If you're asking, "Do you like
this?" That's a task with lots of
variance, so inter-annotator agreement's
not useful. If you're asking, "Is it
factual?" Maybe it should be lower, but
you even if it's zero, you don't know if
you've asked the right question, right?
Or if they're all using ChatGPT, the
variance will also be zero, right? So,
it's very hard to assess quality, even
though there's like ways of maybe
getting at that question.
>> So,
is the reason you're seeing like
annotator
or like companies starting to recruit
more like experts or like highly
educated people for to be annotators
because they
give some of like higher quality or like
more like well-thought-on answers, or is
it because like the data that you're
collecting is for something that like
only these people can answer?
>> I think it's more of the latter. Um, you
know, like maybe you need a lawyer to
check if a Blue Book annotation is
correct. You need to be relatively well
trained to be able to do that. Um,
you know, uh, and there's also sort of
tacit knowledge of various kinds that
maybe you want to extract. So, that's
one of the reasons. It is true that I
think in general the platforms are
moving more towards like higher quality
annotators, even for general annotation
tasks. I think a big part of this is
because LLMs have gotten good, and if
you don't like in-person supervise
people, they will use the cheapest, you
know, LLM to generate possible-looking
answers.
Um, and so I think, you know, there's a
lot of annotator shops whose value
proposition is basically like, "We have
real people that do real things, and we
will verify that this is true for you,
right?"
Cool. Okay, yeah.
>> What's the largest problem in I I know
you might be getting to this. What's the
largest problem in like using a
domain-specific model
um
as an
as an annotator?
>> Um, so the question was, "What's the
problem with using domain-specific
models as an annotator?" I guess there's
two separate questions there. One is
like, "Are domain-specific models good?
And then the other question is like,
should we use models to annotate data?
Um model-based data annotation is quite
good. It's you know, if you're not at
the frontier, and what you want to do is
basically catch up to the frontier,
model-based annotation is very, very
good, right? Modern models are, you
know, probably much, much better than uh
random crowd worker you can get. And so,
model-based annotation's good idea. Now,
domain-specific models, well, can you
get domain-specific models that are
better than, you know, the strong open
models? Sometimes quite difficult. And
so, for that reason, I don't think
there's a unique advantage, for example,
to annotating with domain-specific
models. In general, model-based
annotations are a good idea.
Okay. So, you know, I didn't plant that
question, but we are moving towards uh
model-based annotations now. Um if you
look at LM-generated annotations of
various kinds, you will find that, you
know, these models are surprisingly
good. Um when GPT-4 came out, some of my
students and I did comparisons between,
you know, GPT-4's annotations and
carefully curated human annotations. And
if you compare the rankings of systems,
they're pretty good. If you compare the
agreement between humans to models, the
mode of humans to models, um they're
pretty good, um and their cost is, you
know, a order of magnitude less. So,
that's, you know, all nice and good. And
at the time when we initially did this,
you know, back in the GPT-4 era, it was
still not clear which way things were
going to go. Like in the open world, for
example, were we going to move towards,
you know, expensive human annotation, or
will everything just become, in some
ways, distillation from stronger models?
Um I think at this point, it's been
enough years that we kind of know the
answer, which is, you know, there's
basically no space for human-collected
data, um if all you want to do is to
catch up to the frontier in
capabilities.
I think one of the things that I found
very interesting at the time and sort of
instructive is hugging face was trying
to build a open source model called
Zephyr. And one of the things that they
really wanted to do at the time was to
not do any model distillation. And so
they said, well, we're not going to use
any model based annotations or model
based data.
And we're going to spend a lot of time
and effort collecting human data. So
they went to the same, you know, vendors
that open AI and others do to basically
go and collect a bunch of human data.
But basically they found that it was
extremely time consuming, costly, and
the results they were getting were not
actually better than using model based
annotations. And so in the end, you
know, they basically just used model
based feedback for this, right?
Which I think is instructive. They they
gave it a very real good shot, you know,
using the you know, resources that they
had, but in the end they ended up using
AI feedback.
And this has basically been the case.
Like so, you know, for SFT and also for
RLHF, we find that you know, Ultra Chat
and Ultra Feedback, which are model
generated, are now very standard. Tulu
3, which I I mentioned as like one of
the big, almost flagship open source
post training processes, uses, you know,
model based annotations for all of its
pipeline. And so this is basically where
we we've ended up in terms of, you know,
should we use model based annotations or
not?
Models are very good at following
instructions, very scalable, so you can
collect the right kinds of data that you
want. And this is roughly where
things are. Of course, if you want to
push the frontier out, you don't get to
necessarily play these games except in
limited circumstances. And so you're
still very much rely on human driven
data collection.
Okay. Yeah.
Well, 7B is small now. I guess, you
know, at the time I guess 7B was kind of
a very respectable open source model.
It's like Llama is a 7B, everyone loves
Llama 7B, we too would like to train a
7B. And so, you know, in that sense it
was respectable. Um I don't know if they
they went and tried it for their bigger
runs. Um
but at least at that scale, you know,
they weren't seeing any differences.
Um I would be very surprised if like
they switched to the bigger one and
suddenly there was a big difference. Uh
cool.
Okay. Um there are other places where um
you might do sort of model generation
that is not purely distillation. Um
Anthropic had an early work on
self-training. This was Constitutional
AI, where they kind of prompted a model
to generate safety data, um and then
they trained, you know, the model itself
on that prompted data, um and that
allowed them to get sort of a safer
model uh out of the model. And then you
can think of this as kind of a very
early um self-post training data
generation loop. And the other paper,
sorry, the other project that I
mentioned to you of uh self-instruct,
that's a different kind of
capability-centric version of this kind
of idea. So, you can use models to kind
of bootstrap your own post-training
data, but if you want something like
lawyers or scientists, um you can't, you
know, get world knowledge without, you
know, getting people to annotate. So,
you're kind of stuck, at least for that,
with collecting human uh annotators.
The other thing I'll mention is that
models are also very susceptible to the
same kinds of biases as humans.
Sometimes in ways that are uh quite uh
problematic as well, like even more
problematic. Um there's been a couple
studies on, you know, after this kind of
wave of uh model-generated data stuff
started coming out, showing that
actually, you know, you could just push
length of your responses way out, um and
you would continue to get improvements
in the win rates of sort of model-judged
uh
performance. Um and you know, if you
look, you know, the one outlier here is
uh ChatGPT 3.5, basically saying like,
"Well, they're not just length hacking,
they're actually a model that is
actually better." Um similarly, um,
others showed, uh, this was a very nice
paper, um, showing that you can just
RLHF on length alone and you could do
quite well on many of these benchmarks.
Okay. So, that's roughly the data story,
right? You know, what kinds of who's
collecting the data, you know, what
kinds of things to be, uh, conscious of.
And then now in the remaining time that
I have, I'm going to talk about kind of
the algorithm. Um, I'm only going to
briefly talk about PPO because, you
know, both in the interest of time and
because I'm just going to do a more
extended treatment next lecture. And
then I'll talk a little bit about DPO,
which is the cool, fun bit.
Okay. So, now remember, right? We're in
the RLHF regime. The goal is the
following. Uh, I'm going to maximize
under my policy, um, the reward that I
get by sampling from that policy. And
this is like baby reinforcement
learning, right? Because
people might say we're playing bandits,
like this is not true multi-turn
interesting RL, and that's roughly
right. And so our algorithms will also
be quite simple.
So, the objective that I just showed
you, maximize reward, it appears almost
exactly in the Instruct GPT paper. If
you look at open up open the paper up
and you go to equation two, you'll find
exactly the the kind of thing I wrote
down where you have, you know, you
sample from your RL policy. I want to
maximize my reward, uh, subject to the
second term, which is really just a KL
divergence. It's all that it's saying is
I want to stay close to my pre-trained
model, uh, because I don't want to go
too far and become degenerate.
Um, same thing is true, um, from
Stiennon et al. This is another paper.
Um,
you see, uh, the reward in this case is
a pairwise feedback model that you've
learned. So, you train a binary
classifier on which of a pair of
examples is better, and then you hill
climb on that reward, right? So, very
simple structure that we have.
Now, how do we actually do that hill
climbing? We use an algorithm called
PPO. Um, if you've taken a RL class, you
of course know what PPO is. Um, if you
haven't, I will give you kind of a baby
description of what PPO is. Um, also
you'll have to understand it for the the
assignment. Um, so the very basic
starting point is the policy gradient
identity, right? What I want to do is I
want to maximize my reward sampling from
my policy. How do I optimize that? Well,
you know, everything in machine learning
is gradient descent, so I take
gradients, right? So I want the gradient
with respect to my parameters, and you
can push the gradient in and do the
policy gradient trick, and you can show
that that's equivalent to the equation
on the right, right? It's going to, you
know, take the gradient of my log
probabilities and weigh it by my
rewards. And this really just looks like
SFT, but with weighted examples,
effectively.
Now, you might say, "Okay, policy
gradients are great. I love policy
gradients, but the problem with policy
gradients is I need to sample every time
I want to take a optimization step." And
sampling is very expensive, right? We've
already talked about in the systems
part, inference is often very
complicated and hard, whereas training
is very, you know, arithmetically
intensive and good, right? And so, I
want to roll out once, and I want to
reuse that roll out multiple times. So,
this is something called off-policy.
To do off-policy, I want to sort of take
multiple steps, but not go too far,
because if I go too far, my sort of
estimates of my local rewards kind of
blow up. So, this is something called
TRPO. The basic idea is I want to take
policy gradients, but I want to stay a
little bit close to where I am. Well,
you do something called an importance
weighting correction. Not going to go
into that in detail. Finally, PPO says,
"Well, TRPO is a good idea, but this
sort of, you know, distance constraint
is actually kind of hard to deal with.
And so, I'm going to come up with a
heuristic clipping thing that's just
going to discourage the RL algorithm for
going to places where I'm too far from
the original policy, right?" Um, I'll go
through the details of this in the next
lecture, so you don't need to worry
about it, but the main progression of
policy gradient, off-policy, you end up
at PPO, hopefully you roughly
understand.
Um, PPO, already the equations look a
little bit gnarly, right? And so a lot
of people for many years have asked the
following question, can we get rid of
PPO? And this was a big, you know, thing
for many people.
Um and many reasonable people thought
about lots of good ways of getting rid
of PPO. And I will tell them to you so
that you do not necessarily repeat them
in your own research. Um for example,
you can say I have a pair of examples
and I can do SFT but with a special kind
of SFT. If for the pair that's good, I
will prepend a good token. And for the
example that's bad, I'm going to prepend
a bad token. So you're going to append
some tokens um and then when I generate,
I'm just going to prefix my response
with good so my model only generates
good stuff. So this is reducing PPO to
SFT or RL to SFT. Does not work. Um
people have tried training the model
only on the good stuff. Um also does not
work very well. Um you can train the
reward model, get LM outputs, select
only the stuff that the reward model
selects and train on that. Does not work
as well, although it does somewhat work.
Um so many people have tried many
different iterations and you know, in
the end we do now have a thing that is
much less complex than PPO, works pretty
well and is in many ways looks just like
SFT. Um and this is DPO.
And so the algorithm is very, very
simple. What we're going to do is we're
going to try to get rid of the
complicated parts of PPO. What are we
going to get rid of? We're going to get
rid of the reward model. Um we're going
to get rid of anything that has to do
with on-policy stuff. And by getting rid
of these two things, we're going to try
to make a much more simple uh RLHF
algorithm. Um and it relies on a very
simple intuition, right? Everything in
in deep learning is just taking gradient
steps in the direction of good things.
And so we're going to take steps in the
direction of the log loss of the good
stuff and then we will take negative
gradient steps on the direction of the
bad stuff. In in other words, we're
going to reverse for uh the the log
probability of anything that is bad.
This is
basically the most naive thing you can
do, right? Cuz you're doing SFT on one
hand, and you're doing kind of negative
SFT on the bad thing. Um it turns out
that if you weight these two
appropriately, you will get an algorithm
that is actually pretty good. Um and
I'll give you the derivation cuz it's
all very simple.
Um so, remember, our goal is to optimize
this equation over here, right? So, this
should look familiar to you. The first
term is my expected reward under my
policy pi theta. The second term is
saying that's my KL distance. I want my
uh policy to remain close to my
reference. That's what I pre-trained.
Now, I'm going to make a assumption.
This is the one strong assumption that
I'm going to make, and I'm going to
assume that pi, my policy, is actually
not a neural network at all. It is the
set of all possible policies. It is a
non-parametric thing. It can approximate
anything, right? So, if pi can be
anything, I can actually solve that top
problem closed form, right? I actually
know what the minimizer is. Um and the
minimizer is the following.
The um the minimizer is actually to take
my original reference policy and to
exponentially tilt it by my reward. In
other words, every response gets
upweighted or downweighted um with a
weight exp of 1/beta r, right? Based on
how good the reward is. This makes a lot
of sense. If the reward is really bad,
I'm going to exponentially downweight
it. If the reward's really good, I'm
going to exponentially upweight it,
right? So, this is the closed-form
solution if pi can be anything. Now, we
can then Now that we know this pi of r,
this perfect solution, I can solve for
the implied reward. In other words, I
can solve for what is kind of the um r
that would induce this, and so I can
solve for that, right? I can put the pi
r on the left side, and I can solve for
the reward that we would have.
And then, we can take that implied
reward that I wrote down, um and then I
can solve for what would happen in the
original RLHF objective. I plug in my
reward into that objective here, into my
loss. And this gives the DPO objective,
which is sort of very intuitive.
It basically says take
sort of gradient steps in the positive
direction, and then take negative
gradient steps in the bad direction,
right? And you can kind of already see
what's going to happen. This first term
over here, this is the good stuff. This
is the bad stuff on the right term here,
and they're going to be balancing each
other.
Okay?
And so if I take the gradient of this, I
think this is the most intuitive form of
DPO, at least to me.
You have two things. For every pair that
you've had annotated, I'm going to
increase the likelihood of the the
example that won, and I'm going to
decrease the likelihood of the example
that lost,
and I'm going to scale sort of the step
size in some sense by how much my
implied reward model is wrong. Like did
my model already assign a very high
reward to the winning one? If it did so,
I will take a small step. But if I was
very wrong, and I said, "Oh, these two
are almost equal." I had same
probability, but in that case, I will
actually take a much bigger step size,
right? So based on the probability
differences, I will take bigger or
smaller step sizes on this sort of
differential log prob objective. So
hopefully the the
action of this gradient objective is
quite clear to people.
Okay. So this is actually much much
simpler than PPO, right? Because all I'm
doing is taking gradients, and we all
know how to do that with our standard
processes.
And I think the nice thing is that it
does work reasonably well. I think for
for a while,
people were very obsessed with like, "Is
DPO better than PPO or vice versa?" I
think the answer now is maybe it doesn't
matter very much unless you're like at
the frontier training the very best
model. DPO is is reasonably good, and
it's good enough for for Llama, it's
good enough for me. If you go and open
up the Llama tech report, you'll find,
um, you know, that they basically had
this like nice outer loop training
where, you know, they had their model,
they SFT'd it, they did DPO, and then
they used that DPO model to then sort of
generate candidates that they rejection
sampled, and they repeated this process.
So, there's the outer loop on top of it,
but basically the core RLHF primitive
for Llama was DPO.
Um,
in the year since, uh, there's been a
lot of different variants, um, of DPO.
There was SimPO, which basically changes
sort of the weighting. So, instead of
using pi ref, um, you have this like Y
of L normalizer. Um, there was length
normalized DPO, which normalizes by the
length, um, in order to avoid certain
like length hacking issues that seem to
arise.
Um, but really,
um, none of these variants maybe seem to
matter very much. Um, one of the things
that I'll mention that I thought was
very interesting was these results are
very, very contingent on the specifics
of the experiment setup. So, even at
AI2, you know, uh, there was a paper
that was like, "Well, it turns out that
if you go from DPO to PPO, um, you'll
get a better result." Um, but then, you
know, they also had a paper for for, uh,
Tulu 2 where they said, "Actually, if
you do DPO right, um, you can do better
than PPO." Um, and so, depending on how
you execute this, um, one can be better
than the other. I'm I'm sure you have
experiences reading deep learning papers
and so on where like the results are
very fragile, right? Um, so, maybe the
takeaway from all of this is that these
DPO variants are actually, you know,
close enough to the right thing to give
you pretty good performance in many
cases, right? This core idea of take
gradient step in the right direction and
take negative gradient step from the bad
stuff works reasonably well as long as
you set the step sizes right.
Okay.
I will end with the last few slides on
things to watch out for in RLHF. So, one
of the things to watch out for is
over-optimization. And this is maybe one
of the biggest things.
Um to give you also historical context,
right? When Instruct GPT came out and
like, you know, people were very excited
about this, I think there was a very
real question of like, can we RLHF our
way to like, you know, superintelligent
systems or whatever? Maybe we can just
collect enough thumbs up, thumbs down.
Um turns out that is actually quite
challenging um because you you find that
if you try to like really push the RLHF
process forward, um you'll start
overfitting to your learned reward
model, right? So, the KL regularizer
that I talked about is really critical
in a lot of cases um in order to prevent
your sort of um optimization process
from overfitting
um your reward model. At least if your
if your uh optimization process is very
good.
The other thing that I'll talk about um
is uh model collapse. Um so, people have
seen lots of times where our RL models
have much less diversity. They're like
concentrated on a few different possible
outputs. Um and this connects back to
what I said before, right? RLHF models
um are really no longer modeling a
distribution, which comes with its own
inherent diversity. Uh it's a policy
that can collapse as long as it gets a
good reward, right? So, this is another
thing that that
uh sort of RLHF models have really
struggled with
um in recent years.
Um
So, actually I'm going to I'm going to
skip this cuz it's we're at time. Um and
I think this this entropy and mode
collapse thing actually ends up being
quite important uh even today. Um and
the GPT-4 era actually was one of the
few plots that OpenAI put out where they
said, "Actually, we have a few open
problems left." And one of the open
problems they had was, "Actually, our
models are uncalibrated after we do
RLHF." Which you can see in this plot
over here. Um I don't think anyone has
really solved that yet. Um
the uh Anthropic folks also had a
argument saying like, "Well, it's
naturally uncalibrated. You could
recalibrate sometimes, but not always."
This It very important in the next
lecture when we talk about things like
RLVR where the the entropy and
exploration is actually quite critical
for the model to explore all the
possible solutions and to make progress
on some of these very hard problems.
Great.
Um so to, you know, put it all together,
right? Um
RLHF data collection is also very hard.
I think part of the thing about post
training is it's very complicated messy
process because a lot of it is getting
good data and getting good data is
always very difficult. Um
RLHF algorithms are are quite complex.
PPO is especially difficult. I'll I'll
talk a little bit about it um next
lecture. Thankfully, we do also have a
simpler variant there called GRPO that
works pretty well. That's what you'll do
in your assignments. Um but this is one
place where there's been a lot of recent
developments. Um Finally, I think in
terms of RLHF, the you know, one of the
big big problems is over optimization.
And the transition to the next lecture
is going to be, you know, is there
rewards where we won't over optimize,
right? Where we can just kind of dumping
compute and the model performance just
keeps monotonically getting better. And
that's one of the reasons why uh what
people call RLVR is just so, you know,
been so impactful.
Thanks. See you all Thursday.